<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: fun | mishadoff thoughts]]></title>
  <link href="http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/categories/fun/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mishadoff.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-16T16:06:06+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://mishadoff.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[mishadoff]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DevOps reactions]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/devops-reactions/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-13T18:10:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/devops-reactions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just found blog, that illustrates developer feelings with gif-pictures: <a href="http://devopsreactions.tumblr.com/">DevOps reactions</a></p>

<p>It's really cool idea.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Here are the most liked</p>

<h3>When you review undocumented code</h3>

<p><img src="http://i209.photobucket.com/albums/bb315/DJ_Napps/omg.gif" alt="" /></p>

<h3>Security hole will not be fixed because Product wants a new feature</h3>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/w3Nbr.gif" alt="" /></p>

<h3>An error notification comes in that is related to code you worked on</h3>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/An059.gif" alt="" /></p>

<h3>Code freeze</h3>

<p><img src="http://media.tumblr.com/c888a5fc6db74ba2ba4f5dcb3d13e95b/tumblr_inline_mfrh8jAexq1raprkq.gif" alt="" /></p>

<h3>Working on the wrong server</h3>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/da25D.gif" alt="" /></p>

<h3>Deciding whether to perform a risky break/fix</h3>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/SvaAv.gif" alt="" /></p>

<h3>Finding an interesting side-issue while dealing with something else</h3>

<p><img src="http://www.ohmagif.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/please-wait-i-need-to-play-in-the-puddle.gif" alt="" /></p>

<h3>Reaction difference when something breaks and one is on vacation</h3>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/c9X6n.gif" alt="" /></p>

<h3>Typical lunch break</h3>

<p><img src="http://media.tumblr.com/tumblr_mekc6kZTap1raprkq.gif" alt="" /></p>

<h3>How time feels when participating in a meeting with non-technical people</h3>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/7xpOF.gif" alt="" /></p>

<h3>Bonus: Holy War (Java vs C#)</h3>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/u9CAo.gif" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>P.S.</strong> Everyone can submit feeling.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ingress Tricks]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/ingress-tricks/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-11T12:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/ingress-tricks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ingress - MMORPG with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Augmented_reality">augmented reality</a> created by Google.
This is very impressive game with capability to run over the city with your friends for capturing portals.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/vskNt.jpg?1" alt="" /></p>

<p>The game genre positioned as <strong>MMMMOARG</strong> (<em>massively multiplayer map-based mobile online augmented reality game</em>).
In fact, it's just MMORPG. You have character, you play online with other people.</p>

<h2>Brief game overview</h2>

<p><em>skip if you already now what Ingress is</em></p>

<p>There are two fractions in game: <strong>Enlightened</strong> and <strong>Resistance</strong>.
In few words, Enlightened for a progress and big changes, Resistance for conservative being.
<strong>Portals</strong> are famous places like monuments, memorials, sculptures, etc.
Each fraction can capture portals, improve, destroy them, link portals with each other,
and create control field (<em>by linking three portals in triangle</em>). Area under this control field covers
some number of <strong>mind units</strong>. Fraction that have more mind units - more succesful to achieve its goal.</p>

<h2>Some tricks</h2>

<p>If you already a member of Ingress, check these tricks, probably some you know.</p>

<h2><strong>Resonators</strong></h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Deploy resonator on maximum distance betwen portal.</strong> Because it is much harder for your enemy
to destroy spattered resonators than if they were in one place.</li>
<li><strong>Waste resonators.</strong> If you have no time while running near neutral or low-level
portal, just deploy one resonator of your maximum level. You still can not link it to another portal,
but enemy need to spend enough effort to destroy it.</li>
<li><strong>Upgrade.</strong> Use upgrade menu to improve resonators on portal. If somebody deployed L1 resonator, and you
can change it to L4, it would be good.</li>
<li><strong>Use specific resonators.</strong> By default you deploy only L1 resonators. From upgrade menu you can select
what resonators you want to deploy.</li>
</ul>


<h2><strong>Bursters</strong></h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Do not waste bursters.</strong> It's useless to fire couple bursts if they are not destroying resonators/portals. Just save them.
When you have enough bursters, then you can destroy enemy portal and get XP.</li>
<li><strong>Use bursters from optimal point.</strong> It's opposite from previous. Find place where your bursters' coverage
on enemy resonators will be maximum. Use weighted estimate, you need stand closer to higher level resonators.</li>
<li><strong>Use specific bursters.</strong> By default you fire with you maximum level bursters. If enemy portal not so hard you can
select lower-level burster from weapons menu.</li>
</ul>


<h2><strong>Mods</strong></h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Deploy portal shields.</strong> For portals that have enough support and high level. Portal shields are relatively rare resources, so don't waste them.
Also if you deployed shield on high level portal, much harder for enemy to get resources, and destroy it.</li>
</ul>


<h2><strong>Links</strong></h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Plan links and fields carefully.</strong> You must not be fast at linking, in case you linking more than 4 portals,
there are possibilities. And you should choose one that gives you maximum number of fields.
To make link between A and B, you need portal A with enough distance to B, and portal key from B.</li>
<li><strong>Build long links.</strong> Long links can prevent other fraction to link something.
Because crossed links are restricted. But if you have time to link something better, think about it.</li>
</ul>


<h2><strong>Resources</strong></h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Gather resources.</strong> Find place where you can see a lot of high-level portals and hack them. One hour
spent near them gives you a lot of resources.</li>
<li><strong>Share resources.</strong> You can, or better you need to share resources with your friends. It's cooperative game.</li>
</ul>


<h2><strong>Area</strong></h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Distribute area locally.</strong> Communicate with players from your city and plan what territory can be supported by whom.</li>
<li><strong>Strategic portals.</strong> Don't plan your strategic portals in common places. They can be simply destroyed. Use for your strategic
portals some strange places, like portal inside building, mountain portals, island portals, etc.</li>
<li><strong>Use Intel Map to plan your trip.</strong> Move only in the way you already know. Don't practice <em>blind trips</em>.</li>
</ul>


<h2><strong>Friends</strong></h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Play with friends.</strong> Preferably, the same level friends. Obviously, you can destroy more, you can capture more.
Also, it's more fun to talk with somebody during the moving.</li>
<li><strong>Communication.</strong> If you see somebody playing ingress near you, don't hesitate to meet and make friendship. Even he or she from
another fraction. Maybe it's your future spouse.</li>
</ul>


<h2><strong>Home playing</strong></h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Repair portals.</strong> If you are sitting at office, have enough XM, you still can help your fraction.
Just open portal keys and you can repair these portals distantly. Keep in mind that resonator XM reduces by 10% each day.
The trick is also to repair one most valuable resonator.</li>
<li><strong>Solve puzzles.</strong> If you solve some puzzle that appeared on niantic site or in your inventory, you
can help you fraction a lot by posting code in faction channel.</li>
<li><strong>Manage the actions.</strong> You can sit at home with opened Intel Map and guide somebody to do right things.</li>
</ul>


<p>This post planned to be updatable, because all these advices found upon investigation. Check for new updates.
Also, if you have some useful information, other tips and tricks,  post it in comments.</p>

<h2>Links</h2>

<p>More about game and some useful resources here:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.ingress.com/">Ingress Official</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.nianticproject.com/">History and Puzzles</a></li>
<li><a href="http://ingressfieldguide.com/">Tips &amp; Tricks</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/Ingress">Ingress subreddit</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.ingress.com/intel">Intel Map</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>Bonus: xkcd</h2>

<p><img src="http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/location.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Viva la Resistance!</p>

<p><strong>P.S.</strong> Unfornunately game at closed beta right now. Only for Android devices.
Hope it will be released very soon and we will see more people near monuments.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What is source code?]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/what-is-source-code/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-29T23:31:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/what-is-source-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's not just a bunch of <code>ifs</code> and <code>fors</code> you mastering every day.
It's not even <code>Factories</code>, <code>Builders</code> and <code>Proxies</code> you learn from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Design_Patterns">GoF</a>.</p>

<p>I think this term has much wider meaning.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><em>Almost everything you can create is source code.</em></p>

<p>By creation I mean creation in digital world, not building the house.
Good criteria of source code - is something that may be changed and need to be up-to-date.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/WiredEnterprise/Lord-of-the-Files">Article</a> - source code,
<a href="https://github.com/mishadoff/mishadoff.github.com">Blog</a> - source code,
<a href="https://github.com/patmorin/ods">Book</a> - source code,
<a href="https://github.com/magnars/.emacs.d">Configuration</a> - source code,
<a href="https://github.com/bundestag/gesetze">Laws</a> - source code,
<a href="https://github.com/norinori2222/boyfriend_require/blob/master/README-en.md">Dating request</a> is also source code.</p>

<p>The word <code>code</code> can be confusing, but it is not.</p>

<p><strong>Code</strong> - is just a set of instructions that can be processed by <em>processor</em>.</p>

<p>From that point of view, processor is our brain.</p>

<p>And if you really appreciate your <em>source code</em>, choose appropriate control version system for it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What is greater: e^π or π^e?]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/what-is-greater-e-pi-or-pi-e/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-06T16:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/what-is-greater-e-pi-or-pi-e</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You can answer almost immediately using calculator, but what if you don't have it?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I don't remember the exact origin of this meme, but this situation was almost every time when we played with numbers.</p>

<blockquote><p>-- Propose a number.</p>

<p>-- e<sup>π.</sup></p>

<p>-- Integer, shithead!</p></blockquote>

<p>This even might appear in usual conversations:</p>

<blockquote><p>-- What is her size?</p>

<p>-- e<sup>π</sup></p>

<p>-- So small. I prefer π<sup>e.</sup></p></blockquote>

<p>And a following arguing about <strong>what is greater?</strong> Until we simply compare results using calculator.</p>

<p>Let's see how this problem can be solved without using a calc.</p>

<p><strong>Warning:</strong> Goal of this article not only to show correct solution to the problem, but provide other solutions (<em>even incorrect!</em>) that can convince somebody.</p>

<h2>Origins</h2>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pi">π</a> is the mathematical constant. It's just a number that represents ratio between circle circumference and diameter <code>C/d</code>.
Approximately, equal to <code>3.1415</code>. <a href="http://webdocs.cs.ualberta.ca/~smillie/Pi10000.html">Get more decimal places for FREE!</a></p>

<p><img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/3/36/Pi_eq_C_over_d.svg/600px-Pi_eq_C_over_d.svg.png" width="300" height="300"></p>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/E_%28mathematical_constant%29">e</a> is the harder one. If you sum infinite sequence below, you'll get <code>e</code>.
Approximately, equal to <code>2.7183</code>. <a href="http://apod.nasa.gov/htmltest/gifcity/e.2mil">FREE decimal places without registration!</a></p>

<p><img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/math/8/0/5/8050a584d4b528e6293bf02c34f6e399.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>I'm pretty sure that's more than enough you need to know to solve the problem.</p>

<h2>Google It</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.google.com/#hl=uk&amp;gs_nf=3&amp;tok=WfGdb7x83ofvKLc_85HnIw&amp;cp=5&amp;gs_id=227&amp;xhr=t&amp;q=e^pi+-+pi^e&amp;pf=p&amp;output=search&amp;sclient=psy-ab&amp;oq=e^pi+&amp;gs_l=&amp;pbx=1&amp;bav=on.2,or.r_gc.r_pw.r_qf.&amp;fp=51e735cc3a152124&amp;bpcl=37643589&amp;biw=1280&amp;bih=634">Get answer from google</a></p>

<h2>Rough estimate</h2>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/Jv0W1.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>We can use exponent function on integers, so let's just round the numbers.
<code>3.1415</code> becomes <code>3</code>, <code>2.7183</code> becomes... <code>3</code> also.</p>

<pre><code>3^3 vs 3^3
27 = 27
</code></pre>

<p>They are equal. Wrong answer.</p>

<p>Let's use <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Floor_and_ceiling_functions">floor and ceiling</a> functions.</p>

<p>Floor: <code>floor(e) = 2</code>, <code>floor(π) = 3</code></p>

<pre><code>2^3 vs 3^2
8 &lt; 9
</code></pre>

<p>Ceiling: <code>ceil(e) = 3</code>, <code>ceil(π) = 4</code></p>

<pre><code>3^4 vs 4^3
81 &gt; 64
</code></pre>

<p>Two different results depend on round function that we use. Can't be sure.
Need another method for verification.</p>

<h2>Calculus</h2>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/Low4R.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>This needs basic understanding of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logarithm">logarithm</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Derivative">derivative</a></p>

<pre><code>e^π vs π^e
</code></pre>

<p>Use logarithm property <code>a &lt; b =&gt; log(a) &lt; log(b)</code>, and take <code>log</code> with base <code>e</code> (<code>ln</code>).
Honestly, it's not logarithm property, but <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monotonic_function">monotonic function</a> property. Who cares?</p>

<pre><code>ln(e^π) vs ln(π^e)
</code></pre>

<p>Use logarithm property <code>log_a(a^b) = b</code></p>

<pre><code>π vs ln(π^e)
</code></pre>

<p>Use logarithm property <code>log_a(b^c) = c * log_a(b)</code></p>

<pre><code>π vs e * ln(π)
</code></pre>

<p>Now, people who know value of <code>ln(π)</code> can answer the question. We don't know. Move <code>ln(π)</code> to the left side</p>

<pre><code>π/ln(π) vs e
</code></pre>

<p>Take a look at expression <code>π/ln(π)</code>. Change <code>π</code> to <code>x</code>. Got <code>x/ln(x)</code>. What is it? It's a function!</p>

<p>Let's find extrema of this function <code>f(x)</code>. Take first derivative.</p>

<pre><code>f'(x) = (ln(x) - 1)/(ln^2(x))
</code></pre>

<p>We get extrema at the points where derivative equals to zero</p>

<pre><code>(ln(x) - 1)/(ln^2(x)) = 0
</code></pre>

<p>Ratio number equals to zero if its numerator equals to zero.</p>

<pre><code>ln(x) - 1 = 0
</code></pre>

<p>Move <code>1</code> to the right</p>

<pre><code>ln(x) = 1
</code></pre>

<p>Logarithm equals to <code>1</code> if base equals to argument. Therefore</p>

<pre><code>x = e
</code></pre>

<p>And if you know <code>1/ln(x)</code> behavior, you get that extremum is a minimum of function <code>f(x)</code>.
Substitute <code>x</code> with <code>e</code></p>

<pre><code>e/ln(e) = e
</code></pre>

<p>Function minimum is <code>e</code> where <code>x = e</code>. If <code>x = π</code>, due to minimum, function value will be <strong>greater than</strong> <code>e</code>.
Remember that we do this to get estimate of <code>π/ln(π)</code> which was on the left side of expression <code>π/ln(π) vs e</code> and if its <strong>greater than</strong> e,
<code>e^π</code> greater than <code>π^e</code>. Huh. Done.</p>

<p><strong>Note:</strong> We skip mathematical proof that extrema <code>x = e</code> is minimum. Not hard to show.</p>

<h2>Manual computations</h2>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/tTTCC.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Why don't we perform calculation manually?</p>

<p>Ok, we have <code>π</code>, which is <code>3.1415</code> or <code>22/7</code> its famous simplest ratio approximation.
On the other side we have <code>e</code>, which is <code>2.7183</code>. But I'm not aware of any <code>e</code> approximation.
Let's create one from the definition of <code>e</code>. Take and sum first 5 elements.</p>

<pre><code>1 + 1 + 1/2 + 1/6 + 1/24 = 65/24
</code></pre>

<p>Excellent. Now we need just compare <code>2.7183^(22/7)</code> and <code>3.1415^(65/24)</code>. What can be simpler?</p>

<p>Rational exponent can be expanded as nth-root of some power:</p>

<p><img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/math/a/4/3/a43d1edf99a795101aa58ce39cc72f52.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>To take n-th root manually we use a special case of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newton%27s_method">Newton's method</a>.
Just one iteration:</p>

<p><img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/math/a/2/5/a25d581b7161170fc8ab0dbe74532ecc.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Estimate for <code>e^π</code>:</p>

<pre><code>2.7183^(22/7)
sqrt_7(2.7183^22)
</code></pre>

<p>...Multiplying 22 times...</p>

<p>In fact, not all so bad. To calculate <code>a^22</code> we need only 6 multiplications:</p>

<pre><code>a^1 * a^1 = a^2
a^2 * a^2 = a^4
a^4 * a^4 = a^8
a^8 * a^8 = a^16
a^16 * a^4 = a^20
a^20 * a^2 = a^22
</code></pre>

<p>Nth-root we obtain (<em>decimal dropped</em>):</p>

<pre><code>sqrt_7(3585440111)
</code></pre>

<p>Applying Newton's method. Select closest root:</p>

<pre><code>1^7 = 7 &lt; 3585440111
2^7 = 128 &lt; 3585440111
3^7 = 2187 &lt; 3585440111
...
23^7 = 3404825447 &lt; 3585440111
24^7 = 4586471424 &gt; 3585440111
</code></pre>

<p>Good. Most closest value is <code>23</code>. Then</p>

<pre><code>sqrt_7(3585440111.25)
sqrt_7(23^7 + 180614664)
23 + 180614664/(7 * 23^6)
23 + 180614664/1036251223
23 + 0.17
23.17
</code></pre>

<p>And the same for <code>π^e</code>:</p>

<pre><code>3.1415^(65/24)
sqrt_24(3.1415^65)
</code></pre>

<p>This power <code>65</code> much larger than <code>22</code>. But it needs just 7 multiplications.</p>

<p>We can cheat here. We get rough result <code>2 * 10^32</code>. Now we test <code>23^24</code> (<em>most closest root from previous</em>) and its value <code>4.8 * 10^32</code>.
So, definitely nth-root will be lower than <code>23</code>. Solved.</p>

<p>Don't ask how many basic arithmetic operations we performed. A lot.</p>

<h2>Liar approach</h2>

<p>Actually, it's offensive to use the word "liar".
There is a whole technique called <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mathematical_fallacy">Mathematical Fallacy</a>.
It based on some illegal math transformation (<em>division by zero, roots from negative numbers, etc.</em>) to get <strong>any desired result</strong>.</p>

<p>This is powerful instrument for mathematicians to show magic for not mathematicians.</p>

<p>Suppose, we don't know exact value of π. Not a problem, but we know <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Complex_number">complex numbers</a>.
And also the fact that <code>sqrt(-1) = i</code>. Where <code>i</code> is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imaginary_unit">imaginary unit</a></p>

<p>We have bad memory and can't remember π value, but we know <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euler%27s_formula">Euler's formula</a></p>

<pre><code>e^(i * x) = cos(x) + i * sin(x)
</code></pre>

<p>x is a variable. Take <code>x = 2π</code>:</p>

<pre><code>e^(2π * i) = cos(2π) + i * sin(2π)
</code></pre>

<p>From the school math course we know: <code>cos(2π) = 1</code>, <code>sin(2π) = 0</code>. Just substitute:</p>

<pre><code>e^(2π * i) = 1 + i * 0
</code></pre>

<p>Everything multiplied by <code>0</code> is <code>0</code>. Next step:</p>

<pre><code>e^(2π * i) = 1
</code></pre>

<p><code>a^b</code> gives <code>1</code> if <code>b = 0</code>. That we also know from logarithms.</p>

<pre><code>2π * i = 0
</code></pre>

<p>It means either <code>2</code> or <code>π</code> or <code>i</code> is zero. <code>2</code> is not zero. <code>i</code> is not zero. <code>π</code> we don't know.
Ok, that means <code>π</code> equals to <code>0</code>.</p>

<p>Returning to comparing our constants:</p>

<pre><code>e^0 vs 0^e
</code></pre>

<p>Left term is <code>1</code>, right is <code>0</code>. That means <code>e^π</code> <strong>greater than</strong> <code>π^e</code>.</p>

<p>The trick that we used hard to spot. Look carefully again through the proof.</p>

<p>The fallacy was where we implicitly took a logarithm and said that <code>2π * i = 0</code>.
The number <code>e^(2π * i)</code> is not real and we not allowed to logarithm it.
But if person who listens you don't know this fact... This is an excellent proof.</p>

<h2>Programming approach</h2>

<p><img src="http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/e_to_the_pi_minus_pi.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>You not allowed to use calculator. Nothing said about programming language.</p>

<p>One-liner in Java:</p>

<p><code>java
System.out.println(Math.pow(Math.E, Math.PI) &gt; Math.pow(Math.PI, Math.E));
</code></p>

<h2>Fun approach</h2>

<p>Derived from joke:</p>

<blockquote><p>Scientific lab wasted a lot of money for calculating decimal places of π. They come up with idea, let's π will be equal to 4, to save money.</p>

<p>-- But why 4 instead of 3?</p>

<p>-- Because 3 reserved for e.</p></blockquote>

<p>That way <code>e^π</code> equal to <code>81</code>, and <code>π^e</code> equal to <code>64</code>. <code>81 &gt; 64</code>. Simple, concise way.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>There are much more fun about these irrational bastards. Math is fun.</p>

<p>If you were asked question of such type on interview, 99% that interviewer is joking and want to test your reaction.
Last solution would be good. But if he or she really expect solution with using calculus, nothing to lose.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
