<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: clojure | mishadoff thoughts]]></title>
  <link href="http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/categories/clojure/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mishadoff.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-20T17:25:52+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://mishadoff.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[mishadoff]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Clojure Euler: Problem 007]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/clojure-euler-problem-007/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-20T15:37:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/clojure-euler-problem-007</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>By listing the first six prime numbers: 2, 3, 5, 7, 11, and 13, we can see that the 6th prime is 13.</p>

<p>What is the 10001st prime number?</p></blockquote>

<p>Permalink: <a href="http://projecteuler.net/problem=7">http://projecteuler.net/problem=7</a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>It's also pretty clear problem to make you more familiar with prime numbers.
As I said in <a href="/blog/clojure-euler-problem-003">Clojure Euler: Problem 003</a>,
big amount of Project Euler problems devoted to prime numbers so it is <strong>MUST HAVE</strong> (<em>I don't like this phrase either</em>)</p>

<p>You need to implement by yourself effective prime number algorithm. And only after that use one from library.
As we do.</p>

<p><code>clojure
(:use [clojure.contrib.lazy-seqs :only (primes)])
</code></p>

<p>This line import just one symbol <code>primes</code> to your namespace. It's a prime numbers lazy sequence. Lazy sequences briefly covered
in <a href="/blog/clojure-euler-problem-002">Clojure Euler: Problem 002</a> or <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lazy_evaluation">Wikipedia article</a>,
that's enough for now.</p>

<p>Return to question.</p>

<blockquote><p>What is the 10001st prime number?</p></blockquote>

<p>No problem.</p>

<p><code>clojure
(last (take 10001 primes))
</code></p>

<p>Two lines of code: one for import, one for solution. What can be simpler?</p>

<p>Note, that <a href="http://clojuredocs.org/clojure_core/clojure.core/last">last</a> return last element of the sequence and works in linear time.</p>

<p>Another one problem solved in few <strike>seconds</strike> minutes.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/mishadoff/project-euler/blob/master/src/project_euler/problem007.clj">GitHub</a></p>

<p><strong>P.S.</strong> Actually, I lied. In linked solution I use 6 lines of code: namespace declaration, use, <em>empty line</em>,
comment with executing time, function declaration and, finally, solution.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Clojure Euler: Problem 006]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/clojure-euler-problem-006/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-17T14:05:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/clojure-euler-problem-006</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>The sum of the squares of the first ten natural numbers is,</p>

<p>1<sup>2</sup> + 2<sup>2</sup> + ... + 10<sup>2</sup> = 385</p>

<p>The square of the sum of the first ten natural numbers is,</p>

<p>(1 + 2 + ... + 10)<sup>2</sup> = 55<sup>2</sup> = 3025</p>

<p>Hence the difference between the sum of the squares of the first ten natural numbers and the square of the sum is 3025 − 385 = 2640.</p>

<p>Find the difference between the sum of the squares of the first one hundred natural numbers and the square of the sum.</p></blockquote>

<p>Permalink: <a href="http://projecteuler.net/problem=6">http://projecteuler.net/problem=6</a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>This problem is very simple, even simpler than previous one, that confirms fact that all Project Euler problems
are <strong>NOT</strong> in increasing complexity order. Ok, let's split our problem into two subproblems.</p>

<h3>Sum of the squares</h3>

<p>First, we need a square function:</p>

<p><code>clojure
(defn sqr [n] (* n n))
</code></p>

<p>Then, sum of squares of the first one hundred natural numbers we calculate with common <code>(reduce + list)</code> idiom:</p>

<p><code>clojure
(reduce + (map sqr (range 1 101)))
</code></p>

<h3>Square of the sum</h3>

<p>Just take a sum, and square it:</p>

<p><code>clojure
(sqr (reduce + (range 1 101)))
</code></p>

<h3>Bind all together</h3>

<p>We splitted our problem into two smaller, now is time to bind all. We can just subtract results obtained
but you see, that both of smaller solutions uses common piece of code <code>(range 1 101)</code>. Move it to <code>let</code> form.</p>

<p><code>clojure
(let [rn (range 1 101)]
  (- (sqr (reduce + rn)) (reduce + (map sqr rn)))))
</code></p>

<p>That' all. I've got result in less than millisecond.
Maybe there are some pitfalls in this problem (<em>e.g. integer overflow for larger ranges</em>)
but this most straightforward solution works fine.</p>

<p>Congratulations!</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/mishadoff/project-euler/blob/master/src/project_euler/problem006.clj">GitHub</a></p>

<p><strong>P.S.</strong> First time I solved this problem and was confused: <em>Where is the trick?</em> Seems nowhere.
That's why using most straightforward solution is often the best choice (<em>excluding obvious cases, of course</em>).
It has fast implementation, and if it fails, it fails fast.</p>

<p><strong>Fail Fast, Succeed Faster</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Clojure Euler: Problem 005]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/clojure-euler-problem-005/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-09T19:01:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/clojure-euler-problem-005</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>2520 is the smallest number that can be divided by each of the numbers from 1 to 10 without any remainder.</p>

<p>What is the smallest positive number that is evenly divisible by all of the numbers from 1 to 20?</p></blockquote>

<p>Permalink: <a href="http://projecteuler.net/problem=5">http://projecteuler.net/problem=5</a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>It's a tricky problem. First look gives us straightforward solution:
Take a number, test if it evenly divisible by all of needed numbers, if yes - we good,
otherwise increment number and test again, and again, and again...</p>

<p>No, really, assume it's our function to test divisibility by all 20 numbers:</p>

<p>``` clojure
(defn evenly-divisible-by-20? [n]
  (zero? (reduce +</p>

<pre><code>(for [i (range 2 21)]
  (mod n i)))))
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Awful implementation, but keeps the idea.
If sum of all remainders equals to zero, then every remainder equals to zero.
Now, using this function we write naive implementation:</p>

<p>``` clojure</p>

<pre><code>(first
  (drop-while #(not (evenly-divisible-by-20? %)) (iterate inc 1)))
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Note, function <a href="http://clojuredocs.org/clojure_core/clojure.core/drop-while">drop-while</a>
similar to take-while, but skips values until they meet predicate condition.</p>

<p>Waiting for result? Take a cup of tea and wait a little. Still waiting? Wait a little more...</p>

<p>I did not post exact answer here, but result greater than 100 millions.
And obviously this linear algorithm will work considerable amount of time.
So, stop the execution and let's see at the problem from the other end.</p>

<p><em>What is the smallest number that evenly divisible by 1 and 2?</em>
Obviously 2.</p>

<p><em>What is the smallest number that evenly divisible by 2 and 3?</em>
A bit harder, but answer is 6.</p>

<p><em>What is the smallest number that evenly divisible by 4 and 5?</em>
20.</p>

<blockquote><p>Oh, it's just multiplication</p></blockquote>

<p>Unfortunately, no. Take numbers <code>4</code> and <code>6</code>, multiplication gives us <code>24</code> and it will be evenly divisible by <code>4</code> and <code>6</code>, but
this number is not the <em>smallest</em>. Snmallest number for this case will be <code>12</code>.</p>

<p>There is a function, that finds smallest number divisible by 2 different numbers.
This function called <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Least_common_multiple">Least Common Multiple</a> (<em>lcm</em>).
There are lot of different methods to calculate it, but we will use one that uses
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greatest_common_divisor">Greatest Common Divisor</a> (<em>gcd</em>)</p>

<p><img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/math/5/b/3/5b3f3c62dd59cc5594af7b2ece3798fb.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Where <em>gcd</em> calculated according to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euclidean_algorithm">Euclid's algorithm</a></p>

<p>``` clojure
(defn gcd [n k]
  (loop [a n b k]</p>

<pre><code>(if (zero? b) a (recur b (mod a b)))))
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Using formula above, our <em>lcm</em> function will look like this:</p>

<p><code>clojure
(defn lcm [n k]
  (/ (abs (* n k)) (gcd n k)))
</code></p>

<p>You see, here we need <code>abs</code> function. Nothing hard to implement it, but if we remember
<a href="/blog/clojure-euler-problem-004">previous problem</a> there are was a reference
to <code>clojure.contrib.math</code> library. <code>abs</code> there and we can use it, just add to your namespace definition</p>

<p><code>clojure
(:use [clojure.contrib.math])
</code></p>

<p>Oh look, even <code>lcm</code> and <code>gcd</code> functions there. Excellent.</p>

<p>Now we can solve the problem. Remember the <code>reduce</code> function?</p>

<p><code>clojure
(reduce lcm (range 1 21))
</code></p>

<p>Actually, this one-liner is solution. And it gives us correct result.</p>

<p>What happens here? We iteratively (<em>with using reduce</em>) find the lcm for <code>1</code> and <code>2</code>,
then for result and <code>3</code>, for result and <code>4</code> and so on.</p>

<p><strong>Great!</strong> One more problem solved!</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/mishadoff/project-euler/blob/master/src/project_euler/problem005.clj">GitHub</a></p>

<p><strong>P.S.</strong> One lesson we learned here. Be aware about library functionality. It helps you
to solve problems and avoid coward mistakes. For example, we have incorrect above implementation
for <code>lcm</code> function. If we call <code>(lcm 0 0)</code> program fails with <code>DivideByZero</code> exception.
It still solve our problem, but in future uses can be an additional problem.
But in lib implementation this error is covered. And we can be sure that <em>almost always</em> libs contain much less
errors that your <em>new fancy wheel</em>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Clojure Euler: Problem 003]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/clojure-euler-problem-003/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-30T19:12:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/clojure-euler-problem-003</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>The prime factors of 13195 are 5, 7, 13 and 29.</p>

<p>What is the largest prime factor of the number 600851475143?</p></blockquote>

<p>Permalink: <a href="http://projecteuler.net/problem=3">http://projecteuler.net/problem=3</a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>If you familiar with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prime_number">prime numbers</a>, you apparently know basic algorithms to find them,
if not, I advice to get familiar with it. There are lot of problems devoted to prime numbers on Project Euler. So, read 10 minutes about prime numbers, and go on.</p>

<p>In few words, prime number is a number starting from 2 that has no divisors except <em>1</em> and <em>itself</em>.
Exposing this logic on all numbers, we can simply find first prime numbers: <code>2, 3, 5, 7, 11, ...</code></p>

<p>To implement function that search for prime numbers we can implement predicate, that test whether number is prime or not:</p>

<p>``` clojure
(defn prime? [n]
   (= 2 (reduce +</p>

<pre><code>            (for [i (range 1 (inc n))]
              (if (= 0 (mod n i)) 1 0)))))
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>We iterate from 1 up to number and calculate reminder of division number by iteration counter.
If result is zero we return 1, otherwise we return 0.
For each number we get list with length of that number that marked with 1 for exact divisors.
For example for <code>6</code> list will be <code>(1 1 1 0 0 1)</code>, and for <code>7</code> list will be <code>(1 0 0 0 0 0 0 1)</code>.
Than we calculate sum of this list, which represents number of divisors. If count is two, that means number is prime.
This is simplest algorithm for testing prime number, built from prime number definition.</p>

<p>Performing small optimization you can see that in lists above, first and last elements are always equals to 1.
We can just drop them. Another optimization is we don't need go on when we found at least one remainder.
And I'm pretty sure you can find lot of flaws in this implementation.</p>

<p>But the most useful optimization is assumption that we don't need iterate to <code>n</code>, we can iterate to <code>sqrt(n)</code>.
This is based on fact that if we found some number <code>a</code> that is divisor of <code>n</code>, then there is another number <code>b = n / a</code>.
And <code>b</code> is also divisior of <code>n</code>. Little transformation gives us <code>a * b = n</code>. Assume <code>a &lt; b</code>, so if we found <code>a</code> we don't need to seek for <code>b</code>.
Number <code>n</code> is not prime. Maximum value of a achieved when <code>a</code> equals to <code>b</code>, <code>a^2 = n</code>, <code>a = sqrt(n)</code>.
This is reduce complexity of algorithm from <code>O(n)</code> to <code>O(sqrt(n))</code>.</p>

<p>In <a href="http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/clojure-euler-problem-002/">previous problem</a> we mentioned <code>clojure.contrib.lazy-seqs</code> package,
where we have primes lazy sequence. Let's use it!</p>

<p>Algorithm for solving our problem is following:</p>

<ol>
<li>Iterate through all prime number that less than square root of number</li>
<li>If this number is divisor add it to list</li>
<li>Find maximum from that list</li>
</ol>


<p>To transform statements above into clojure, we get:</p>

<p>``` clojure
(defn greatest-prime-of [number]
  (reduce max (filter #(zero? (mod number %))</p>

<pre><code>                  (take-while #(&lt; % (sqrt number)) primes))))
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Something new here:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://clojuredocs.org/clojure_core/clojure.core/max">max</a> - function that returns the greatest number of its arguments.</li>
<li><a href="http://clojuredocs.org/clojure_core/clojure.core/zero_q">zero?</a> - predicate that test whether number is equal to zero or not.
The same as <code>#(= 0 %)</code>.</li>
<li><a href="http://clojuredocs.org/clojure_contrib/clojure.contrib.math/sqrt">sqrt</a> - function from <code>clojure.contrib.math</code>. Name is obvious.</li>
</ul>


<p>Now, we want to find result. Run the line</p>

<p><code>clojure
(greatest-prime-of 600851475143))
</code></p>

<p><strong>Congratulations!</strong> Third problem solved.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/mishadoff/project-euler/blob/master/src/project_euler/problem003.clj">GitHub</a> for lazy!</p>

<p><strong>P.S.</strong> Instead of using <code>clojure.contrib.math</code> for square root we could just write <code>(Math/sqrt n)</code> and got rid of dependency.
But for me is better to reuse something that was implemented in library. It's tested and worked, where your implementation can miss some point.
If you have time, dig more into <code>clojure.contrib.math</code>. It needs about 9 minutes. There are only 9 functions,
but you will probably reinvent them all the time:
<a href="http://clojuredocs.org/clojure_contrib/clojure.contrib.math/expt">expt</a>,
<a href="http://clojuredocs.org/clojure_contrib/clojure.contrib.math/abs">abs</a>,
<a href="http://clojuredocs.org/clojure_contrib/clojure.contrib.math/sqrt">sqrt</a>,
<a href="http://clojuredocs.org/clojure_contrib/clojure.contrib.math/round">round</a> and others.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Clojure Euler: Problem 002]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/clojure-euler-problem-002/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-15T18:46:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/clojure-euler-problem-002</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Each new term in the Fibonacci sequence is generated by adding the previous two terms. By starting with 1 and 2, the first 10 terms will be:</p>

<p>1, 2, 3, 5, 8, 13, 21, 34, 55, 89, ...</p>

<p>By considering the terms in the Fibonacci sequence whose values do not exceed four million, find the sum of the even-valued terms.</p></blockquote>

<p>Permalink: <a href="http://projecteuler.net/problem=2">http://projecteuler.net/problem=2</a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>This is not hard problem with objective to make you familliar with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fibonacci_number">Fibonacci numbers</a>
(this numbers will appear in a lot of next problems). It can be implemented with the straightforward manner with the following rules applied:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>F(0) = 1</code></li>
<li><code>F(1) = 1</code></li>
<li><code>F(n) = F(n-1) + F(n-2)</code></li>
</ul>


<p>So, we can define simple recursive function to calculate n-th number of Fibonacci sequence in clojure:</p>

<p>``` clojure
(defn fib [n]
  (if (or (= n 1) (= n 0)) 1</p>

<pre><code>(+ (fib (- n 1)) (fib (- n 2)))))
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>It's probably not the best implementation of Fibonacci numbers, but it shows the idea.
We can check that it works correctly by calling <code>(map fib (range 10))</code> that produces sequence <code>(1 1 2 3 5 8 13 21 34 55)</code>.
Problem appears when we try to calculate <code>40th</code> number. Calling that function on my machine takes ~20 seconds. Not good.</p>

<p>The reason of such bad performance is repeated calculations. Let's see how expanded call <code>(fib 40)</code>.
It produces <code>(+ (fib 39) (fib 38))</code>, where <code>(fib 39)</code> expanded to <code>(+ (fib 38) (fib 37))</code> and <code>(fib 38)</code> to <code>(+ (fib 37) (fib 36))</code> etc.
The growth with factor of 2. And with these two expansions we calculated 2 values that we calculated before, <code>37th</code> and <code>38th</code>.</p>

<p>We can make better if we producing our sequence in direct order, instead of reverse. This way function will be more complex than previous:</p>

<p>``` clojure
(defn fib-seq [n]
  ((fn [a b c seq]</p>

<pre><code>(cond (= 1 n) [1]
      (= c n) seq
      :else (recur b (+ a b) (inc c) (conj seq (+ a b)))))
</code></pre>

<p>   1 1 2 [1 1]))
```</p>

<p>Let's see what's new clojure features we used:</p>

<ol>
<li>We define function inside function. Why we did this? All is because we used "helper"-function for accumulate current Fibonacci sequence.
It used only in function <code>fib-seq</code>, so we don't need to define it at the root level. It closed for using for everyone, except <code>fib-seq</code>.</li>
<li>Next thing we define anonymous function by keyword <code>fn</code>. Basically it's the right thing to define functions. <code>defn</code> just shortcut for <code>(def (fn [] ))</code>, and..</li>
<li>..we pass default (initialization) values for helper function <code>1 1 2 [1 1]</code>.</li>
<li>I skip logic of helper function here. It is pretty straightforward, just notice two new clojure functions that we used.</li>
<li><a href="http://clojuredocs.org/clojure_core/clojure.core/cond">cond</a> - similar to switch-case structure in C-style languages.</li>
<li><a href="http://clojuredocs.org/clojure_core/clojure.core/conj">conj</a> - add value to collection. Dependant on collection type,
insert new value in different places. For our case we using vector, so we add this value to the end of vector.</li>
</ol>


<p>Now we can call <code>(fib-seq 40)</code> and it calculates all 40 values very quickly. Nice.</p>

<p>But let's return to problem description <em>"... whose values do not exceed 4 million..."</em>.
How do we know how many values we need to take that do not exceed 4 million? 50? 100? 112?
This is drawback of our <code>fib-seq</code> function and we need to rewrite it...or take a look at clojure mechanism called lazy sequences.</p>

<h3>Lazy sequences</h3>

<p>In few words, lazy sequence is infinite sequence of some values, that calculates due to some expression.
The main idea here is the word <em>lazy</em> that means we evaluate expressions when they are needed.
For example, sequence of natural numbers is a lazy sequence. Clojure supports lazy sequences along with operations on them.
So, we can combine sequences, limit, filter etc. Java do not support lazy sequences but similar functionality can be implemented with generators concept.
Generator interface provides method <code>next()</code> to retrieve next value in the sequence, and that method evaluates value.
But this approach is very poor with comparison to clojure lazy sequences.</p>

<p>Lazy sequences in clojure can be treated like ordinary sequences. Obviously some methods make no sense, due to infinity of sequence (<code>count</code>, <code>last</code>, etc.)
There are way to define lazy sequences by using macro <code>lazy-seq</code>. But most common way to do it with the function iterate.
It takes function <code>f</code>, and initial value <code>a</code>, and produces lazy sequence <code>(a, f(a), f(f(a)),...)</code>.
For example lazy sequence of natural numbers we can define as following: <code>(iterate inc 1)</code>. Then we can play with this sequence as we want.</p>

<p><strong>WARNING:</strong> <em>Never call lazy sequence without limiting functions. It tries to evaluate all, and... You know, never call.</em></p>

<p>Now, we have a little understanding what lazy sequence is, and can implement Fibonacci lazy sequence.</p>

<p><code>clojure
(defn fib-seq-lazy []
  (map first (iterate (fn [[a b]] [b (+ a b)]) [1 1])))
</code></p>

<p>Ok, What's here:</p>

<ol>
<li>Read from the end. We apply anonymous function to vector <code>[1 1]</code> and produce lazy sequence with <code>iterate</code>.</li>
<li>Note double square brackets in anonymous function definition. Outer brackets indicate function variables.
Inner brackets indicate that we take one parameter to function as argument.
This parameter is a sequence and we map to <code>a</code> and <code>b</code>, first and second elements in that sequence.
For example for first call, <code>a</code> bound to <code>1</code>, <code>b</code> bound to <code>1</code>.</li>
<li>Our iterate produces lazy sequence with following format <code>([1 1] [1 2] [2 3] [3 5] [5 8] ...)</code>.
Our Fibonacci sequence is just first value of each pair, and we using...</li>
<li><a href="http://clojuredocs.org/clojure_core/clojure.core/map">map</a> - takes function and applies it to each element of collection.
This function also produces lazy sequence.</li>
<li>To gather all in one we get lazy sequence that represent Fibonacci numbers <code>(1 1 2 3 5 8 ...)</code>.</li>
</ol>


<p>Now we have to implement functionality that in problem description. Immediately, code:</p>

<p><code>clojure
(reduce +
  (filter even? (take-while #(&lt; % 4000000) (fib-seq-lazy))))
</code></p>

<p>Another one(<em>two</em>)-liner. Good.</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="http://clojuredocs.org/clojure_core/clojure.core/take-while">take-while</a> - takes values from sequence (includes lazy sequences) while condition is true.</li>
<li><code>#(&lt; % 4000000)</code> - <code>#()</code> it's <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tautology_%28rhetoric%29">shorter shortcut</a> for anonymous function.
In our case predicate return true if value lower than 4 millions. Exacly what we need.</li>
<li><a href="http://clojuredocs.org/clojure_core/clojure.core/filter">filter</a> - return all values for which predicate return true.
Instead of take-while it proceed all sequence till the end, and, obviously, do not accept lazy sequences.</li>
<li><a href="http://clojuredocs.org/clojure_core/clojure.core/even_q">even?</a> - predicate that return true, if number is even.
Note: this is common way to append function name with question mark to indicate that this function is predicate (return true or false). Just convention.</li>
<li>And, finally, sum all of them.</li>
</ol>


<p><strong>Congratulations!</strong> We just solved Project Euler Problem 2.</p>

<p>There are also few optimisations to get result faster, but <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KISS_principle">KISS</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/mishadoff/project-euler/blob/master/src/project_euler/problem002.clj">GitHub</a> for lazy!</p>

<p><strong>P.S.</strong> We could use <code>clojure-contrib</code> library, which is often deployed with standard <code>clojure-core</code>.
<code>clojure-contrib.lazy-seqs</code> library contains method <code>(fibs)</code> that also produces lazy Fibonacci sequence.
And interestingly it implemented the same way as we did.
There are two more lazy sequences: prime numbers and powers of 2.
It's good practice to use existing functionality and not invent vehicle.</p>

<p>Have fun!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
