<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: life | mishadoff thoughts]]></title>
  <link href="http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mishadoff.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-05T01:34:00+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://mishadoff.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[mishadoff]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learn Perl]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/learn-perl/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-12T20:38:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mishadoff.github.com/blog/learn-perl</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><code>perl
($current_tasks, $perl) = ($perl, $current_tasks);
</code></p>

<p>Long time learning <a href="http://www.perl.org/">perl</a> was my desire.
Now I pushed back for a little some of my activities, and started with perl.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The reason for this was the third launch of <a href="https://class.coursera.org/crypto-004/class/index">Stanford Cryptography</a> class on coursera.</p>

<p>Cryptography is a field that I never know, but would like to. I see a lot of practical applications here,
but, honestly, for me it’s more <em>just for fun</em>, than anything else. Isn’t it interesting to (de)cypher something?</p>

<p>First two launches was marked as lack of time for me, so I postponed it. By the way, other interesting courses was <em>in progress</em>.
But now I really hope that I get enough time (<em>and patience</em>) to finish the class and get some good knowledge in this field.</p>

<p><img src="http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/lisp.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>I don’t know why, but I choose perl as primary language for doing programming assignments.</p>

<p>First of all, I needed some fast scripting language for general-purpose problems. To choose between perl and python, I choose perl.
Because of <em>“less number of symbols in the name”</em>, of course. Second of all, I don’t know perl and it’s a good reason to learn it <em>in action</em>.
Also, what is important, I did get only positive reviews from my friends who know perl, but all their stories was like a mistery for me.
Thought, that only chosen one can learn perl. I want to dispel this myth. To try, at least.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There’s more than one way to do it</p>

  <p>– Perl motto</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The book that I choose for learning is a classic book (<em>read Perl Bible</em>) from the creator of perl, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Larry_Wall">Larry Wall</a>.
There is fresh, 4th edition, available.</p>

<p><a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/9780596004927.do"><img src="http://akamaicovers.oreilly.com/images/9780596004927/cat.gif" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Hope, I won’t stop at the middle of something and get useful tool for <em>everyday problems</em>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
