<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: thoughts | mishadoff thoughts]]></title>
  <link href="http://mishadoff.github.io/blog/categories/thoughts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mishadoff.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-22T01:17:26+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://mishadoff.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[mishadoff]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Heisenberg Principle]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishadoff.github.io/blog/heisenberg-principle/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-21T00:24:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mishadoff.github.io/blog/heisenberg-principle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is so obvious, so I decided to write about it.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/pxxRKNR.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uncertainty_principle">Heisenberg principle</a>
came from quantum mechanics and means that you can’t know exactly
both coordinates and speed of particle. If you improve accuracy of detecting
position, you lose accuracy in detecting speed and vice versa. <em>Uncertain</em> stuff.</p>

<p>In human-readable form it sounds like</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Either one or the other</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The same in every field, even in software engineering.
If you implementing something or fixing bugs and your boss
yelling: “you must work <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gAjR4_CbPpQ">better and faster</a>”
tell him <em>either one or the other</em>.</p>

<p><strong>P.S.</strong> Actually, you can say “go fuck yourself”, but it won’t be polite.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Programming Digest Announcement]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishadoff.github.io/blog/programming-digest-announcement/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-11T23:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mishadoff.github.io/blog/programming-digest-announcement</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently, I come up with idea to share my favorite articles I found
on the internet and give basic description for them.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I do not plan this <em>digest</em> as periodical thing,
so the first pattern I found appropriate is to publish this as soon
as I have ten articles marked as <em>favorite</em> somewhere.</p>

<p>That’s the rule: <strong>each post - 10 articles</strong>.</p>

<p><em>Favorite</em> means <em>really favorite</em>, so I do not crosspost every article I’ve read.</p>

<p>Hard to say what topics will be covered.
I call it <em>programming digest</em> because most of articles will be somehow
related to programming, but do not blame me if you see articles with another
topic (math or humour), believe me they can be interesting also.</p>

<p>By the way, a lot of articles may be old, even very old (<em>don’t call me Necromancer</em>)
but if they appear here, I found them somehow relevant and important to post.</p>

<p>Hope, you’ll find such sort of digest is interesting for reading and I like if you
share your favorite <em>programming-related</em> articles with me.</p>

<p>Have fun!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What is source code?]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishadoff.github.io/blog/what-is-source-code/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-29T23:31:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mishadoff.github.io/blog/what-is-source-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s not just a bunch of <code>ifs</code> and <code>fors</code> you mastering every day.
It’s not even <code>Factories</code>, <code>Builders</code> and <code>Proxies</code> you learn from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Design_Patterns">GoF</a>.</p>

<p>I think this term has much wider meaning.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>Almost everything you can create is source code.</em></p>

<p>By creation I mean creation in digital world, not building the house.
Good criteria of source code - is something that may be changed and need to be up-to-date.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/WiredEnterprise/Lord-of-the-Files">Article</a> - source code,
<a href="https://github.com/mishadoff/mishadoff.github.com">Blog</a> - source code,
<a href="https://github.com/patmorin/ods">Book</a> - source code,
<a href="https://github.com/magnars/.emacs.d">Configuration</a> - source code,
<a href="https://github.com/bundestag/gesetze">Laws</a> - source code,
<a href="https://github.com/norinori2222/boyfriend_require/blob/master/README-en.md">Dating request</a> is also source code.</p>

<p>The word <code>code</code> can be confusing, but it is not.</p>

<p><strong>Code</strong> - is just a set of instructions that can be processed by <em>processor</em>.</p>

<p>From that point of view, processor is our brain.</p>

<p>And if you really appreciate your <em>source code</em>, choose appropriate control version system for it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello, world!]]></title>
    <link href="http://mishadoff.github.io/blog/hello/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-10T16:10:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://mishadoff.github.io/blog/hello</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is my first post.
It is always hard to begin something, but I’ll try.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h3 id="why">Why?</h3>

<p>I had blog earlier on <a href="http://mishadoff.livejournal.com">LiveJournal</a>, it was basically in Ukrainian, my native language.
But more time I was working on something, less time I had to write something.
Honestly, it even was not programming specific blog, just random thoughts, xposts, pictures, etc.
You know this shit. Also, it was very hard to maintain some posts, especially about programming, and I gave up.
Excellent proof is my failed attempt to share and explain Clojure solutions on <a href="http://projecteuler.net">Project Euler</a>.
Everything can be a reason: lack of readers, lack of feedback, not interesting topic, very specific topic,
bad writing style, terrible livejournal layout and so on. Probably, these are all my excuses or maybe I just lazy.</p>

<p>Now I’ve got something in my mind and have passion to share it.
No matter if somebody like it or not.
I really believe that if you share something for this world,
sooner or later somebody point you on your mistakes. And it’s a win.
You got knowledge that didn’t know earlier and can share it to someone else. Simple loop.</p>

<h3 id="what">What?</h3>

<p>I plan to be specific in this blog, so a big part will be about programming, especially Java and Clojure.
I also love puzzles and stupid self-made pictures (O_o) and they have reserved place in my blog.
Time to time can appear posts with reference to some clever people, if they have clever thoughts, of course.
Event reports, some critic, books, movies, music, games, humour.
Only God knows what else can appear in my mind and therefore in this blog, but I’ll try to be specific as much as possible.
Really.</p>

<h3 id="english">English?</h3>

<p>As you already understand I’m not native English speaker or writer or whatever. How many mistakes did you count?</p>

<p>I need some effort even for writing simple sentence in English (<em>Kiev is the capital of Ukraine - not this one</em>).
And no matter how long I check my grammar or spelling I will have some mistakes. Big deal.
Improve English is one of my goals, so it’s ok. <em>adding english in todo list</em></p>

<p>I also don’t exclude option, that some posts will be in Ukrainian or even in Russian.</p>

<h3 id="what-else">What else?</h3>

<p>I spent half an hour writing this first post and believe that in near future I have more structured thoughts than this bag of words above.
Good luck and welcome to my blog!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
